Guide to The Nation Institute Oral History Collection on Alger Hiss TAM.709
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
The Nation Institute Oral History Collection on Alger Hiss
2001-2004
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Nation Institute (U.S.)
Ruben, Albert
Kisseloff, Jeff
Polshek, Ellyn
Witty, Margot
TAM.709
2 Linear Feet in 1 record carton and 4 media boxes
43 Cassettes
1.36 Megabytes in 34 computer files
39 interviews on 49 access CDs
The Nation Institute Oral History Collection on Alger Hiss (dated 2001-2004) contains 42 interviews with individuals acquainted with Alger Hiss. Alger Hiss was a State Department official who was accused of Soviet espionage, and was eventually convicted of perjury in 1950. Interviews in the collection were recorded between 2001 and 2004 as part of an oral history project created by The Nation Institute following Hiss's death in 1996, and feature individuals who spent time with Hiss later in his life. Interviewees discuss their personal relationships with Hiss between the 1970s and 1990s, and focus on impressions of him during those years. Several interviewees were among a group of young volunteers who read books to Hiss when he began to lose his eyesight. Many interviews focus on how the interviewees' personal relationships with Hiss shaped their views about the charges against him.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Margot Witty, executive editor of The Alger Hiss Story website, in 2016. The accession number associated with this gift is 2016.050.
Arrangement
Interviews in this collection are arranged in alphabetical order by interviewee last name. Physical transcripts do not follow the intellectual arrangement, and are grouped in booklets in roughly chronological order.
Historical Note
The Nation Institute Oral History Collection on Alger Hiss was created by The Nation Institute with funding from the Isabel Johnson Hiss Fund. The project was initiated shortly after Alger Hiss's death in 1996 to record his friends' and family's memories about him.
Alger Hiss (1904-1996) was a State Department official who served in the administration of Franklin Delano Roosevelt, and was involved in the establishment of the United Nations. In 1948 Hiss was named as a communist by Whittaker Chambers in a hearing before the House Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC). Hiss was called before HUAC to testify and later filed a defamation lawsuit against Chambers. During the trial process Chambers produced evidence that Hiss had been involved in espionage, and in 1950 Hiss was sentenced to three years in prison for perjury.
Related Materials
The Alger Hiss Oral History Collection (TAM 625) contains an incomplete set of interviews from The Nation Institute's Alger Hiss Oral Project that duplicate interviews contained in this collection.
Scope and Contents
The Nation Institute Oral History Collection on Alger Hiss (dated 2001-2004) consists of 41 interviews with individuals acquainted with Alger Hiss. Interviews were conducted between 2001 and 2004 and largely feature individuals who were close with Hiss later in his life. Several of the individuals featured were life-long friends, but others featured are younger individuals who were recruited to read for Hiss as his sight began to fail him in his old age. Interviews focus primarily on the subjects' personal relationships with Hiss, their perceptions of him as a person, his intellectual and literary interests, and his family life. They also feature discussions about Alger Hiss's trials and the continued analysis of the evidence against him. These discussions address topics including Whittaker Chambers's accusations, evidence introduced during the trials, the 1996 release of the Venona papers, Allen Weinstein's book Perjury: The Hiss-Chambers Case, and Russian historian Dimitri Volkogonov.
A large portion of the interviews were conducted by Albert Rubin, who was the first historian working on the Alger Hiss Oral History Project. Other interviews were conducted by oral historian Jeff Kisseloff and Hiss's attorney Ellyn Polshek, both of whom continued the project after Rubin retired in 2002. Interviews are recorded on audio cassette with accompanying physical or electronic transcripts. The interview with Victor Chapin does not have an audio recording and is only available in a transcript.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596, with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596, with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Separated Materials
During processing it was determined that an interview featuring Julius Kobyakov was not created as part of this collection. This interview has been separated and added to an unprocessed collection.
Oral histories (literary works); Trials (Espionage) -- United States.; Communism -- United States -- 20th century; VENONA historical monograph; Hiss, Alger; Chambers, Whittaker; Volkogonov, Dmitri Antonovich.; Weinstein, Allen; Witty, Margot
- Aronson, Grambs, 2001 March; cuid157
  Scope and Contents
  This interview was conducted by Albert Ruben in March 2001. In this interview Grambs Aronson discusses her friendship with Alger Hiss. The bulk of the interview focuses on her personal relationship with Hiss, and her thoughts about the charges against him. She talks about Hiss's personality, how his prison sentence affected him, and her thoughts about Whittaker Chambers. She also talks briefly about Hiss's role in the formation of the United Nations, and the UN 50th Anniversary in 1995.
  Extremely poor audio quality
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 157)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Ashton, Dore, 2001 April 9; cuid158
  This interview was conducted by Albert Ruben on April 9, 2001. In this interview Dore Ashton describes her friendship with Alger Hiss, largely focusing on Hiss's political beliefs and his interests in art and literature. She touches briefly on Hiss's praise of the New Deal and his objection to the policies of Richard Nixon. She also talks about Hiss's reaction to the publication of the book Perjury: The Hiss-Chambers Case by Alan Weinstein. In the final portion she shares as story about a discussion she and Hiss had about a decision by Salvador Allende to resist extradition of a Nazi seeking asylum in Chile.
  Very poor audio quality
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Digital Transcript, TW_TAM_709_ER_1
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 158)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Blum, Penny, 2001 April 20; cuid159
  This interview was conducted by Albert Ruben on April 20, 2001. In this short interview Penny Blum talks about her social relationship with Alger Hiss and his first wife Priscilla. Much of the interview focuses on social engagements with Blum, her husband, and the Hiss family. She also talks about Hiss's political beliefs, and Priscilla Hiss's frustration about the lack of support her husband received from his powerful friends after he was released from prison. Finally she discusses how their friendship ended over a political disagreement between Hiss and her husband.
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Digital Transcript, TW_TAM_709_ER_2
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 159)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Brudney, Karen, 2001 September 22; cuid160
  This interview was conducted by Albert Ruben on September 22, 2001. In this interview Karen Brudney talks about her family's friendship with Alger Hiss. Brudney's parents became friends with Alger Hiss when she was a child, shortly after he was released from prison. In her interview she describes Hiss as an attentive adult, who enjoyed discussing her interest in music when she was young and politics when she got older. She mentions their discussions about Vietnam, Nixon, the Black Power movement, the New Left, and Ronald Reagan. She also talks briefly about Hiss's interest in her work as a doctor in Nicaragua.
  Poor audio quality with electronic interference throughout
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Digital Transcript, TW_TAM_709_ER_3
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 160)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Brudney, Victor, 2001 February 4; cuid161
  This interview was conducted by Albert Ruben on February 1, 2001. In this interview Victor Brudney shares personal anecdotes about his friendship with Alger Hiss, who he met in 1965. Much of the interview focuses on Hiss's close connection to Harvard Law School, where Brudney later went on to teach. He also talks about serving as a witness on Hiss's behalf during his application to be readmitted to the Massachusetts bar in 1974. Brudney shares several personal stories about his social relationship with Hiss, and also discusses Hiss's continued interest in clearing his name, including his attempt to reach out to Russian historian Dimitri Volkogonov, and his interest in the Venona papers.
  Poor audio quality
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 161)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Buttenwieser, Lawrence, 2001 August 16; cuid162
  This interview was conducted by Albert Ruben on August 16, 2001. In this interview Lawrence Buttenwieser talks about his recollections of Alger Hiss and his memories surrounding the Hiss trials. His mother, Helen Buttenwieser, was an attorney for Hiss during his trials. The bulk of the interview focuses on Buttenwieser's impressions of Hiss as a person, his political beliefs, and his intellectual interests. It ends with speculation about how Hiss will be remembered by history.
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Digital Transcript, TW_TAM_709_ER_4
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 162)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Chalif, Ronnie, 2001 May 8; cuid163
  This interview was conducted by Albert Ruben on May 8, 2001. In this interview Ronnie Chalif discusses her long friendship with Alger Hiss. She talks about meeting Hiss in 1955 or 1956, and focuses primarily on their social relationship. Chalif reflects on his personality, interests, and relationships in his family. She talks about his admiration of Oliver Wendell Holmes, his reaction to Nixon's impeachment, and also briefly touches on Hiss's father's suicide and how it affected his childhood.
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 163)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Chapin, Victor, circa 2001-2004; TW_TAM_709_ER_5
  This interview was conducted by an unidentified individual. In this interview an individual only identified as "Victor" talks about the Hollywood Blacklist and the Alger Hiss trials. He talks about his experience as a blacklisted member of the film industry, his film career, his acquaintance with Alger Hiss, and his membership in the Communist Party of the United States of America.
- Collins, Mary Evans, 2001 January 10; cuid779
  This interview was conducted by Ronnie Chalif on January 10, 2001. In this interview Mary Evans Collins discusses her friendship with Alger Hiss and her connection with his family. Collins explains that she met Hiss in 1947 or 1948 through her husband Henry Hill Collins, who was a life-long friend of Hiss. She talks about socializing with Hiss and his wife Priscilla, and later discusses how her husband was also brought to testify in HUAC hearings. The end of the interview focuses on her friendship with Hiss after he was released from prison, and includes discussions about reading to Hiss when he began to lose his eyesight.
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 6, 8)
  - Original Recording (Box 4, Cassette 779)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Crown, Mrs. Rufus, 2001 March 19; cuid164
  This interview was conducted by an unidentified individual on March 19, 2001. In this interview Rufus Crown discusses her friendship with Alger Hiss. She begins the interview by talking briefly about her personal political beliefs and participation in activism with her husband Alfred Crown. She discusses meeting Hiss and his second wife Isabel at a party in the early 1960s, and focuses much of the interview on personal anecdotes about connections with family and mutual friends. She also talks at some length about Hiss's admiration of Franklin D. Roosevelt.
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 164)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 5)
- Geismar, Anne, 2002 September 12; cuid165
  This interview was conducted by Jeff Kisseloff on September 12, 2002. In this lengthy interview, Anne Geismar reflects on her social relationship with Alger Hiss and shares general opinions about his character. Geismar begins the interview by talking about her own life and shares a story about meeting her husband Max Geismar in 1930. She also talks about her early career working at Art Digest. She describes meeting Hiss at a dinner party shortly after he was released from prison, and talks about how she saw his trials as symbolic of the political atmosphere that was dominated by anti-communism. Much of the interview focuses on Geismar's general impressions of Hiss, his friendship with her husband, and Hiss's literary interests.
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 165)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Gelber, Jack, 2001 April 24; cuid166
  This interview was conducted by Albert Ruben on April 24, 2001. In this interview Jack Gelber talks about his acquaintance with Alger Hiss and his personal research into the Hiss trials. Gelber explains that he became well acquainted with Hiss in 1976 when he began writing a play about the Hiss-Chambers case, and was introduced to Hiss by his friend Arthur Penn. In the interview, Gelber does not touch on specific events, but rather discusses his general impressions about Hiss's personality and memory toward the end of his life.
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Digital Transcript, TW_TAM_709_ER_6
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 166)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Grace, Cindy Hiss, 2002 February; cuid167
  This interview was conducted by Ellyn Polshek in February 2001. In this interview Cindy Hiss Grace discusses the impact of the Hiss-Chambers case on her family. Grace is the daughter of Alger Hiss's younger brother Donald. The bulk of the interview focuses on how the Hiss-Chambers case affected her family, and the emotional trauma they experienced from being under FBI surveillance. Grace also talks about other tragedies surrounding the Hiss family, including the suicide of Alger and Donald's father and the deaths of their siblings Mary Ann and Bosley. She also talks about family politics, describing the Hisses as firm supporters of the New Deal and admirers of Justice Oliver Wendell Holmes.
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 167)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Haury, Agnese, undated; cuid196
  This interview was conducted by Jeff Kisseloff. In this two-part interview Agnese Haury talks about working at the United Nations (UN) and her friendship with Alger Hiss. Haury begins the interview with a discussion about her background, and the events that led her to begin working as an editor at the United Nations. She talks about working with Hiss during the early days of the UN, and discusses how staff at the UN viewed the Hiss trials. In the first interview she describes attending several of the trial proceedings, and talks generally about Hiss's initial reaction to the allegations. The second part of the interview focuses more on Hiss's personal relationships. She shares a story about taking Hiss's wife Priscilla and his son Tony to Lewisburg prison following his conviction, and discusses providing the family with financial support. She also talks at some length about Hiss and his brother Donald, and concludes the interview with a discussion about Hiss during the last years of his life.
  - Digital Transcript, TW_TAM_709_ER_7
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 196)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1-4)
- Hobson, Tim, 2002 October 21; cuid168
  This interview was conducted by Jeff Kisseloff on October 21, 2002. In this lengthy three-part interview Tim Hobson talks about his relationship with his step-father Alger Hiss and his memories of the Whittaker Chambers allegations. In the first part Hobson talks about his mother Priscilla Hiss, his father Thayer Hobson, and his relationship with Alger Hiss. The first part of the interview also focuses on the testimony of Whittaker Chambers, and Hobson's memories of the years in which Chambers claimed to be associated with the Hiss family. The second part of the interview largely focuses on Hiss's life after his conviction and his release from prison. Much of this section focuses on family dynamics between Hiss, his son Tony, and his second wife Isabel. The third part of the interview returns to Chambers's account of his relationship with Hiss and contains some more pointed questions about the degree to which his testimony conflicts with Hobson's memories.
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 168 A-C)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1-5)
- Horan, Tim, 2001 May 1; cuid169
  This interview was conducted by Albert Ruben on May 1, 2001. In this interview Tim Horan talks about his friendship and business relationship with Alger Hiss. He explains that he met Hiss in 1960, when Hiss came to his office selling stationery. Much of the interview focuses on Horan's perception of Hiss as a person and his political beliefs. At the end of the interview Horan discusses Whittaker Chambers's accusations against Hiss and provides an assessment of Chambers's personality. Finally he talks about Hiss's decision not to have his step-son Tim Hobson testify on his behalf.
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Digital Transcript, TW_TAM_709_ER_8
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 169)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Lane, Lynn, 2001 April 23; cuid170
  This interview was conducted by Albert Ruben on April 23, 2001. In this interview Lynn Lane discusses her friendship with Alger Hiss. She talks about meeting Hiss at a dinner party after he had been released from prison, and largely focuses on her perceptions of his personality. She talks generally about his interest in other people, his political leanings, and his literary interests. Lane also discusses her long-held belief in Hiss's innocence, but notes that in recent years she has questioned whether his account was entirely truthful.
  Electronic hum heard on and off throughout entire interview
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Digital Transcript, TW_TAM_709_ER_9
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Cassette 170)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Levine, Alan, 2001 November 9; cuid171
  This interview was conducted by Albert Ruben on November 9, 2001. In this brief interview Alan Levine talks about his experience as a reader for Alger Hiss. Levine explains that he volunteered to read for Hiss after reading his second autobiography, in which Hiss talked about performing the same service for Justice Oliver Wendell Holmes when his eyesight faded. In this interview Levine shares several anecdotes about Hiss, speaking about his views on politics in the early 1990s, and Hiss's work as a court reporter at the Rosenberg case. The interview closes with a discussion about the books Levine and Hiss read together and the other volunteers who read to him.
  Electronic hum heard throughout
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Digital Transcript, TW_TAM_709_ER_10
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Cassette 171)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Lundquist, Oliver, 2002 November 15; cuid172
  This interview was conducted by Jeff Kisseloff on November 15, 2002. In this interview Oliver Lundquist talks about Alger Hiss's role in the formation of the United Nations. Lundquist begins the interview by talking about his own background as a design student in New York in the 1930s and explains how he later began working in the design department for the Office of Strategic Service (OSS) during World War II. Lundquist describes meeting with Hiss in 1944 when he was working for the Visual Presentation Division of the OSS. He talks about Hiss's work at the Dumbarton Oaks Conference and his role in leading several early United Nations meetings. The interview also touches on Lundquist's relationship with Hiss, who he describes as a mentor. Lundquist also talks about his opinion of Hiss's innocence and talks at length about typewriter forgery. He concludes the interview by talking about the 50th anniversary of the United Nations and Hiss's physical condition toward the end of his life.
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Digital Transcript, TW_TAM_709_ER_11
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Cassette 172)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Magdoff, Harry, circa 2003; cuid780
  This interview was conducted by Jeff Kisseloff in 2003. In this interview Harry Magdoff talks about his friendship with Alger Hiss, who he met at a dinner party in the 1950s. Magdoff begins the interview by sharing a story about his acquaintance with Harry Dexter White, who was also named as a Communist by Whittaker Chambers. Magdoff also talks about accusations of communist espionage that he faced, and talks about how that experience built a mutual understanding between Hiss and himself. He also talks generally about his social relationship with Hiss, and shares his opinions about him as a person.
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Digital Transcript, TW_TAM_709_ER_12
- Navasky, Victor, 2001 September 20; cuid173
  This interview was conducted by Albert Ruben on September 20, 2001. In this interview Victor Navasky talks about his friendship with Alger Hiss and his continued interest in the Hiss trials. The bulk of the interview focuses on research into the evidence against Hiss and includes discussions about Allen Weinstein's book Perjury, John Lowenthal's research on Alger Hiss and the Venona Papers, and Russian historian Dimitri Volkoganov. Navasky also shares an anecdote about inviting Hiss to lecture for a course he taught at Swarthmore College. He concludes the interview by talking generally about his belief in Hiss's innocence and how his research has informed that belief.
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Digital Transcript, TW_TAM_709_ER_13
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Cassette 173)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Novick, Tillie, 2002 September 6; cuid174